Guide to The Charles M. Lefferts Military Uniforms Print Collection 1880-1926 (bulk 1900-1926) PR 99
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
The Charles M. Lefferts Military Uniforms Print Collection
1880-1926 (bulk 1900-1926)
PR 99
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.1 Linear feet (5 boxes)
Collection of printed unsewn signatures, half-tone reproductions of original illustrations, and photographic copies of original illustrations, principally from the 1926 book, "Uniforms of the Armies of the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783" by Charles M. Lefferts, as well as reproductions of illustrations by Lefferts for other projects, and illustrations compiled by him of military uniforms by other artists.
Provenance
Gift of the Estate of Charles M. Lefferts, 1923.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Biographical Note
Charles MacKubin Lefferts was born in New York City on April 19, 1873, the son of Marshall Lefferts, Jr., and Clara Walker Fay Lefferts. On his mother's side he was a descendant of Captain Josiah Fay of Ward's Massachusetts Regiment in the American Revolutionary War.
Lefferts was always keenly interested in military affairs. In 1893 he enlisted as a private in the 7th Regiment National Guard, State of New York, and served five years before being honorably discharged. He re-enlisted for one year in 1901. With the outbreak of World War I, Lefferts wanted to fight for his country but his age prevented him from serving in the ranks in France. He re-enlisted for federal service in 1917 and served until 1921 rising to the rank of Lieutenant. The year of his retirement he received a state decoration for long and faithful service.
Other than a brief engagement as a salesman for the American Woolen Company, Lefferts dedicated most of his life outside the military to the study of the uniforms worn in the American Revolutionary War. He was a tireless researcher, devoted to the accuracy of his descriptions and illustrations. Lefferts was a self-taught artist with natural capabilities, but he hoped his images would be judged according to the information they contained rather than their aesthetic qualities. He began with the study of the British army in America, which he contended was always his primary interest. With time, however, the scope of his project grew to include four countries involved in the war and all the variations of military dress. For nearly thirty years, he searched archives in England, France, Germany, and United States, gathering details of the great variety of uniforms worn by the various armies for different purposes throughout the war.
Lefferts was elected a member of The New-York Historical Society in 1909. Recognizing the value of his knowledge, the Society requested that he produce a series of illustrations based on his research. Lefferts died at Port Washington, Long Island on March 17, 1923. The New-York Historical Society published his images and descriptions three years later under the title Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783.
Scope and Content Note
The Charles M. Lefferts Military Uniforms Print Collection spans the period from 1880-1926 and contains military uniform illustrations made and collected by Charles Lefferts.
Series I. Material from Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783, contains printed materials related to this book, published in 1926 by the New York Historical Society. The book is a compilation of the illustrations made by Lefferts of the uniforms of the American, British, French, and German armies during the American Revolution accompanied by his descriptions of the uniforms and the units that wore them.
Series II. Photographs of Lefferts' Illustrations of Scenes of War contains photographic copies of paintings made by Charles Lefferts from 1916-1921 for Rodman Wanamaker, the president of Wanamaker's department store on Broadway in New York City.
Series III. Uniform Illustrations by Other Artists includes printed illustrations, dated 1880-1923, which were collected by Lefferts.
Series IV. Duplicates contains duplicates of materials found in Series I.
Arrangement
The collection is divided into 4 series.
Series I. Material from Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783
Series II. Photographs of Lefferts' Illustrations of Scenes of War
Series III. Uniform Illustrations by Other Artists
Series IV. Duplicates
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
The original watercolor illustrations by Lefferts which were reproduced in Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783 are in the New-York Historical Society's Museum Collection. The Museum Collection also includes artifacts donated by the estate of Charles Lefferts.
Military uniformsâUnited States; Photographic prints; United States--History--Revolution, 1775-1783; United States. Continental Army--Uniforms
- Series I. Material from Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains printed materials related to this book, published in 1926 by the New York Historical Society. The book is a compilation of the illustrations made by Lefferts of the uniforms of the American, British, French, and German armies during the American Revolution accompanied by his descriptions of the uniforms and the units that wore them. Included in Series I is the prospectus for the book, also published in 1926, which announces the plan for the publication with the title Uniforms of the American, British, French and Hessian Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783. The prospectus describes the historical value of Lefferts' work and the remarkable extent of his research. As an example of the content of the proposed volume, an illustration and description of New York Artillery Company, Captain John Lamb, 1775, is provided. Also provided is a list of the uniforms that would be covered in the book. The prospectus states that the volume would be produced if a sufficient number of subscriptions were sold at the cost of $25.00 each. Series I also includes illustration plates printed for the book, which were perhaps proofs or extras, that have been mounted on cardstock with printed captions. This series also contains unbound signatures from the book that similarly appear to be extra copies. Neither the plates nor the unbound signatures form a complete set although there are many duplicates of particular items in each group.
  - Prospectus, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Unbound signatures, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Plates, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 3-5)
- Series II. Photographs of Lefferts' Illustrations of Scenes of War
  Series II contains photographic copies of paintings made by Charles Lefferts from 1916-1921 for Rodman Wanamaker, the president of Wanamaker's department store on Broadway in New York City. Wanamaker commissioned a total of fifty-three watercolor and oil painting illustrations from Lefferts to be used for window display and public exhibition throughout the store. At the time of the closing of Wanamaker's in 1954, twenty-eight of the drawings remained in possession of the store. The paintings were photographed by the New-York Historical Society in 1955. The paintings were later sent to other Wanamaker stores in Westchester County, NY, and Philadelphia. The majority of the drawings depict scenes from the American Revolution although several show scenes from World War I. Each of the images is accompanied by a descriptive caption written by Lefferts. These illustrations are mentioned in the introduction of Uniforms of the Armies in the War of the American Revolution, 1775-1783.
  - Reproductions of images made for Rodman Wanamaker, 1916-1921 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Series III. Uniform Illustrations by Other Artists
  Series III includes printed illustrations, dated 1880-1923, which were collected by Lefferts. Illustrations are arranged alphabetically by country. The majority of the images have been mounted on cardboard. The material includes several sets of illustrations including French and German sets that provide information the country, regiment, and date of the uniform in those languages. There is also material from a variety of other sources. These include clippings, postcard, magazine art, and one group of four albumen photographs that are studio portraits of German officers.
  - Austria-Hungary, [1900-1923] (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - France, [1900-1923] (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
  - Germany--Troops Involved in American Revolutionary War, [1900-1923] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Germany--Early 19th Century (1801-1848), [1900-1923] (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Germany--Late 19th Century and WWI, [1880-1923] (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Italy, [1900-1923] (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Prussia--Early 18th Century (1709-1745), [1900-1923] (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Prussia--Late 18th Century (1756-1790), [1900-1923] (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Spain, [1900-1923] (Box 3, Folder 17)
- Series IV. Duplicates
  Series IV contains duplicates of materials found in Series I.
  - Prospectus, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - Prospectus, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 21-22)
  - Unbound signatures--frontispiece, 1926 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 1-22), 1926 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 71-86), 1926 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 103-118), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 119-134), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 152-166), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 183-198), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 199-214), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Unbound signatures--(p. 215-230), 1926 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Unbound signatures--fold-out, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Unbound signatures--index, 1926 (Box 5, Folder 33)